Inventory of the Klaus Kirchner collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Soviet Central Series, 1941-1945; 1-5 (Box 1-5:)
  - WOHIN NUN?..., 1944 November (Folder 5: 3190)
    13x18 cm - 2 - paper: blue - preservation: 1. Description: [Where to now?... Dissociate with the moribund Hitler-clique. Hitler and his accomplices feel their end is near... This is why the Hitler-clique started the "Volkssturm" as a last resort... They want to win time to prepare their flight. German officers and soldiers! Men of the "Volkssturm"... Make an end to the war! This is your last resort...]. Drawing.
  - Himmlers "Volkssturm", 1944 November (Folder 5: 3191)
    13x16 cm - 2 - paper: yellow - preservation: 1. Description: [Himmler's "Volkssturm". "Come on out, whatever is crawling and flying…" The mightiest wonder weapon of the German Reich will be employed: the Volkssturm"...]. Drawing, a poem, a parody on Volkssturm, on reverse.
  - Generalfeldmarschall PAULUS an das deutsche Volk Deutsche! Anfang..., 1944 November (Folder 5: 3193)
    15x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Fieldmarshal Paulus to the German people. Germans! At the beginning of August.. ']. Portrait photograph of Paulus.
  - "Wir stehen nun wieder ganz allein an der... Der Karren ist festgefahren.", 1944 November (Folder 5: 3196)
    17x14 cm - 2 - paper: yellow - preservation: 1. Description: [''Now, we are completely alone at the front fighting our enemies," Hitler. The cart has broken down...]. Drawing, see similar leaflet code 2742. Here only one "horse" i.e. Hungary, is remaining.
  - Was sagt Generalfeldmarschall Paulus über den "Volkssturm"?, 1944 November (Folder 5: 3200)
    12x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [What General Fieldmarshal Paulus says about the Volkssturm? Germans! Hitler and his clique know very well they have lost the war. No measures taken can change that...]. Portrait photograph Paulus.
  - Was sagt Generalfeldmarschall Paulus über die russische Kriegsgefangenschaft?, 1944 November (Folder 5: 3201)
    11x16 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [What General Fieldmarshal Paulus says about Russian captivity?... Each of you know Hitler has lost the war... Do not believe the Nazi-lies that Russians are treating their POWs inhumanely... POWs are not forced with a whip and a shot in the neck to do propaganda against their fatherland...]. Portrait photograph Paulus, see above.
  - Generalfeldmarschall Paulus weist dem deutschen Volke den Weg!, 1944 November (Folder 5: 3202)
    11x16 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [General Fieldmarshal Paulus is showing the German people the way!... All of you have this question burning in your hearts: What is the way out of this war Hitler has lost, what is the salvage?... Nazi-propagandists want to frighten you with the terror of defeat... Paulus says:... There is only one way out... Parting from Hitler and ending the war!...]. Portrait photograph of Paulus, see also leaflet code 3200.
  - Schauermärchen der Hitlerfaschisten über angebliche Greueltaten der Sowjettruppen..., 1944 November (Folder 5: 3205)
    9x17 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler Fascists spread alleged horror stories of war crimes committed by Soviet troops... Hitler Fascists intend to incite soldiers and civilians to continue the war... Nobody will believe Hitler's henchmen from Katyn, Babi-Yar and Maidanek...]. The leaflet is reporting on a film project Hitler-Fascists are producing. The title is "Greueltaten der Sowjettruppen in Ostpreussen" [Atrocities of Soviet troops in East Prussia]
  - Der 27. Jahrestag der Grossen Sozialistischen Oktoberrevolution..., 1944 November (Folder 5: 3206)
    20x25 cm - 8 - preservation: 1. Description: Stalin's report on the occasion of the 27th anniversary of the Russian Revolution... [On the fortification and enlargement of the anti-German coalition. Questions of peace and security...]
  - Öffentliche Erklärung deutscher Generale..., 1944 November (Folder 5: 3218)
    15x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Public declaration of German generals and officers about living conditions of German POWs in Soviet Russia. Because the German government is refusing to accept mail from German POWs in Russia, it is erecting an artificial wall between POWs and their relatives. Everything said in Germany about alleged mistreatment of German POWs is a lie...]
  - Das Jahr ununterbrochener Niederlagen..., 1944 November (Folder 5: 3219)
    11x15 cm - 4 - paper: red, paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [The year of Hitler's unrelenting defeats...]. Quotes of passages of Stalin's report on the occasion of the 27th anniversary of the Russian Revolution.
  - Hitlerdeutschland von zwei Fronten umklammert Deutsche Offiziere und Soldaten!, 1944 November (Folder 5: 3220)
    17x13 cm - 2 - paper: blue, rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler-Germany encircled on two fronts...]. Quotes of passages of Stalin's report on the occasion of the 27th anniversary of the Russian Revolution.
  - Hitlers letzte Karte ist geschlagen Deutsche Offiziere und Soldaten! Alle..., 1944 November (Folder 5: 3221)
    17x13 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler played his last card...]. Quotes of passages of Stalin's report on the occasion of the 27th anniversary of the Russian revolution.
  - Die Hitlerclique hat alle Völker der Welt gegen Deutschland aufgebracht..., 1944 November (Folder 5: 3222)
    17x12 cm - 2 - paper: red, paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler's clique mobilized all nations of this world against Germany…]. Quotes of passages of Stalin's report on the occasion of the 27th anniversary of the Russian Revolution.
  - Die Tage des Hitlerschen Blutregimes sind gezählt. Deutsche Offiziere und Soldaten! Hitlers..., 1944 November (Folder 5: 3223)
    14x11 cm - 2 - paper: red, paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [The days of Hitler's blood regime are numbered...]. Quotes of passages of Stalin's report on the occasion of the 27th anniversary of the Russian Revolution.
  - Worauf hofft Ihr noch?, 1944 December (Folder 5: 3234)
    13x18 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [What is it you are hoping for? To incite you to spend your blood uselessly Nazi propaganda is raising false hopes. See the value of these hopes yourself. Volkssturm?... Wonder weapons?... Insurmountable walls?... Quarrels among the Allies?... Remember: Only he can save himself who ceases to believe in Hitler, he who is breaking with Hilter]
  - DEUTSCHE GENERALE ÜBER DIE RUSSISCHE KRIEGSGEFANGENS, 1944 December (Folder 5: 3236)
    13x19 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [German generals on Russian captivity... Draw your own conclusions from what your generals in Russian captivity tell you. Follow their call!...]
  - Grüsse aus russischer Kriegsgefangenschaft... ihre Angehörigen in Berlin..., 1944 December (Folder 5: 3239)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Greetings from Russian captivity... for relatives living in the city of Berlin... Try to get our lists of POWs! Inform the relatives of POWs!]. These lists of German POWs consist of about 70 names and addresses of relatives of POWs.
  - TEHERAN UND SEINE FOLGEN Was wurde in Teheran beschlossen?..., 1944 December (Folder 5: 3242)
    19x13 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Teheran and its results. Which decisions had been reached in Teheran?...]. Two maps of Germany.
  - An Volk und Wehrmacht Moskau, 8. 12. 1944. Deutsche! Aus tiefer Sorge..., 1944 December (Folder 5: 3252)
    17x25 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description: [To the people and Wehrmacht. Moscow, 8.12.1944...]. Declaration of German generals in Russian captivity. Typewritten text. Facsimiles of signatures.
  - An Volk und Wehrmacht Moskau, 8. 12. 1944. Deutsche! Aus tiefer Sorge..., 1944 December (Folder 5: 3253)
    As above, but 2 pages, different layout and photograph instead of facsimiles.
  - Generalsworte, die in Erfüllung gingen Offiziere und Soldaten! Im Juli..., 1944 December (Folder 5: 3261)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Words of generals that came true...]. The leaflet compares words of German generals from July 1944 with the military situation at the end of 1944.
  - Soldat! Du willst wissen; Zu welchem Zweck hat Hitler den Krieg..., 1945 January (Folder 5: 3280)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Soldier! You want to know: 1. For what reason Hitler began the war? 2. Is there a slightest sign of hope Hitler can escape defeat? 3. Why does Hitler continue the lost war? 4. Will Germany perish if it ends the lost war? 5. What is the way out?...]
  - Volkssturmmänner! Viele von Euren Kameraden sind schon nicht mehr am..., 1945 January (Folder 5: 3284)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1 - 1.1945 - description: [Men of the Volkssturm! Many of your comrades are already dead. Thousands of German Volkssturm men perish uselessly every day...]
  - An die Offiziere und Unteroffiziere der deutschen Wehrmacht..., 1945 January (Folder 5: 3285)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [To the officers and non-commissioned officers of the German Wehrmacht... It would be ridiculous to ignore the enormous superiority of the Red Army and the complete impotence of the German Wehrmacht... Capitulation and imprisonment! There is no other way!...]
  - Rette Dich, ehe es zu spät ist! Soldat! Von der Wolga his zur Oder sind es..., 1945 January (Folder 5: 3300)
    10x15 cm - 2 - paper: yellow - preservation: 1. Description: [Save yourself before it will be too late! The distance from the river Volga to the river Oder is 2000 kilometers, from the Oder to Berlin 75 ... The Red Army has occupied all fortifications... and crossed the Oder river, she will also occupy the last fortification: Berlin... Don't wait until the Russians, British and Americans have destroyed the last pocket...]
  - Soldat! WEISST DU schon etwas über die Krim-Konferenz? Anfang Februar..., 1945 February (Folder 5: 3301)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [...What do you know about the Crimea-Conference?... Do you know what was decided at the Crimea-Conference about Germany and the German people?... Soldier, have you thought what your fate will be?...]
  - Aus ist es mit allen Illusionen! Soldat! VOR KURZEM NOCH fütterten..., 1945 February (Folder 5: 3303)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Not long ago the Nazis told you the illusion about alleged discrepancies among the Allies. Now these illusions have vanished...]
  - Hitler ist Dein Feind! Mach Dich los von ihm! Soldat! Hitler ist Dein Feind..., 1945 February (Folder 5: 3304)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler is your enemy! Free yourself from him!... He has brought the war to the heart of Germany... He has torn you from your family...]
  - BLICK AUF DIE KARTE! SIE HAT DIR VIEL ZU SAGEN, SOLDAT!..., 1945 February (Folder 5: 3305)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Have a look at this map! It will tell you a lot, soldier! One month of the unchecked offensive of the Red Army..]. Map: frontline 12 January to 12 February 1945.
  - ERKLÄRUNG DER FÜHRER DER DREI VERBÜNDETEN MÄCHTE..., 1945 February (Folder 5: 3306)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: blue, red - preservation: 1. Description: [Declaration of the three leaders of the United Nations. In the first half of February a conference took place in the Crimea... Cease resistance... Any other way will lead to your extinction.]
  - Die Russen im Vorgelände von Berlin. DEUTSCHE OFFIZIERE UND..., 1945 February (Folder 5: 3310)
    14x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Russians are approaching Berlin. German officers and soldiers! You all should know what the Supreme Commander of the Red Army, Marshal Stalin, said on February 25, 1945... We have made our way to the approaches to Berlin... The complete victory over the Germans is quite near... Lay down your weapons and go together into captivity. This is the only way to your safety!...]
  - Wir haben die Kriegspläne der..., 1945 February (Folder 5: 3312)
    10x14 cm - 2 - paper: blue, red - preservation: 2, crinkled, discolored. Description: [''We have agreed on the war plans for the final destruction of the common enemy..."]. Quote from the declaration of the Crimea conference.
  - Zu unseren Zielen gehört nicht die..., 1945 February (Folder 5: 3314)
    10x14 cm - 2 - paper: blue, red - preservation: 1. Description: ["It is not our aim to annihilate the German people. Our irrevocable aim is to annihilate German militarism and Nazism and guarantee that Germany will never again be able to disturb the peace of the World"...]
  - Denk an Deine Familie! Soldat! Jetzt..., 1945 March (Folder 5: 3318)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Think about your family! Soldier! Now your wife and your child are at risk. Where are they today?... Who is responsible for their suffering? Hitler!...]
  - DER STAND DER FRONTEN Zur Zeit der Teheraner Konferenz..., 1945 March (Folder 5: 3319)
    20x14 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [The situation at the fronts. At the time of the Teheran Conference. At the time of the Crimea Conference]
  - UNNÜTZE HOFFNUNGEN!..., 1945 March (Folder 5: 3320)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Hopes are in vain! Unnecessary dread! Soldier! Hitler's war is lost without hope. You see that yourself. Why do you continue your resistance?... Unnecessary dread: the German people will not be annihilated. Only Nazism and the German militarism will be annihilated... Think about it: Time is running out! The Russians are at the doors of Berlin...]
  - Die Russen im Vorgelände von Berlin... Stalin über die Ergebnisse des..., 1945 March (Folder 5: 3324)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Russians in the approaches to Berlin...], see also leaflet 3310, different layout.
  - Kapitulation der einzige Weg zur Rettung! Soldaten! Wenn ihr noch nicht..., 1945 March (Folder 5: 3328)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Capitulation, the only way to safety! Soldiers!... Force your officers to capitulate immediately or discuss captivity among fellow soldiers...]
  - Was sagen Eure Generale über die russische Kriegsgefangenschaft?..., 1945 March (Folder 5: 3329)
    30x22 cm - 2 - brown - preservation: 2, edge damaged, no loss of text. Description: [What do your generals say about Russian captivity?...] Eight photographs of generals in Russian captivity.
  - Organisierte Kapitulation Eure Rettung..., 1945 March (Folder 5: 3333)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Organized capitulation is your safety...]. Photograph of German POWs after the capitulation of Bunzlau garrison.
  - Volkssturmmänner! Tausende deutscher Volkssturmmänner, alt und jung, gehen täglich..., 1945 March (Folder 5: 3334)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1 - paper: rose - description: [Men of the Volkssturm! Thousands of German men of the Volkssturm, old and young, perish every day senselessly... What is the use of all the the Nazis tell you, you are defending Germany. This is a lie! It is too late now to defend Germany... The Nazis tell you, the Allies would annihilate the German people. This is also a lie!... The Nazis tell you, you are defending your future. This is also a lie!... Today it is possible tomorrow it might be too late!...]. Photograph of Volkssturm men in Russian captivity.
  - Die Wahrheit über die Lage in den von der Roten Armee besetzten..., 1945 (Folder 5: 3339)
    15x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 2, folded worn. Description: [The truth about the situation in the areas occupied by the Russian Army... The Hitler propaganda started an intensive hate campaign for the dissemination of lies about the conduct of the Russian Army in occupied German areas... What is really happening in German towns and villages occupied by the Red Army?...]
  - 1945 Weg mit dem Bankrotteur! Deutsche! HITLER IST EUER FEIND!... (Folder 5: 3346)
    15x21 cm - 2 - brown - preservation: 1. Description: [1945 - Away with the defaulter! Germans! Hitler is your enemy... Hitler's days and the days of his Nazi-clique are numbered... Cease all resistance against the Red Army! This will help to better the situation for you and your home country...]
  - Warnung der Regierungen der Sowjetunion, der Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika und Grossbritanniens..., 1945 (Folder 5: 3356)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Warning of the government of the Soviet Union... In the name of all United Nations at war with Germany... to all German commanders, guard personnel and men of the Gestapo... Stalin... Truman... Churchill]
- Miscellaneous leaflets series, 1941-1945; 5
  Contains German propaganda leaflets addressed to Russian soldiers and Soviet leaflets addressed to Finnish, Italian, and Romanian soldiers
  - German propaganda leaflets for Russian soldiers, 1941-1945 (Folder 5)
    Five leaflets in Russian
  - Soviet propaganda leaflets, 1941-1945 (Folder 5)
    - For Finnish soldiers (Folder 5)
      Five leaflets in Finnish
    - For Italian soldiers (Folder 5)
      One leaflet in Italian
    - For Luxembourg (Folder 5)
      Two leaflets in Russian and French
    - For Romanian soldiers (Folder 5)
      Two leaflets in Romanian